[MARY]
I'm not sure why,
perhaps it was
the effect of living
in the humdrum world of a
boarding school for so long.
But I always wanted to
see the outside world.
So I attended
university in Paris.
While there, I discovered
a newfound sense of freedom
I had never experienced.
[MARY] And I also
discovered something else.
[MARY] I became swept up
in the fervour around me,
without fully understanding it,
and even participated in the
university clubs'
student activism.
I can't stress enough, the most
I did was distribute leaflets.
However...
[gun fires]
[MARY]
...the group included radicals,
and the officers were planning
to engage in subversive acts.
[MARY]
Then, some days ago,
I was visited out of the blue
by a man calling
himself Milverton,
saying that he had a register
from the organisation
with my name on it.
Now, wait! The Milverton?
Isn't he a newspaper tycoon?
A man who runs
multiple media outlets
has chosen to blackmail you.
To what end? He's mad.
[HOLMES]
I knew it.
Charles Augustus Milverton,
he lives up to his
second persona indeed.
[HOLMES]
The King of Blackmailers.
[HUDSON, WATSON gasp]
[HOLMES]
Milverton is a disease.
He derives pleasure from
watching others fall to ruin,
and nothing else.
He revels in it.
[WATSON] This doesn't
change a thing, really.
I don't care whether or not
all of London knows.
I won't back out
of our marriage.
As for the French government,
they may not share your opinion.
[WATSON grunts]
She'll likely be extradited
and thus, the two of you
will be separated.
Making married life
somewhat difficult.
[WATSON gasps]
[HUDSON] The treasure,
there's no way of recovering it?
So it's impossible to meet
this blackmailer's demand.
[knocking]
[gasps]
[HOLMES] Uncanny timing,
almost as if it were planned.
How good of you to make the
trip all the way to my office,
Mister Milverton.
A meeting one might
say is long overdue,
Mister Sherlock Holmes.
Hm? And who is this gentleman?
Doctor John H. Watson to you.
Ah, I see!
So that would make you
dear Miss Morstan's fiancé.
This is quite the lovely
business we're in, isn't it?
[WATSON] What're we discussing
here? The blasted weather?
Moving on, I suspect you
know why I called on you.
As an informed man,
I've received word
the Treasure of Agra resides
at the bottom of the Thames.
Before we discuss that,
I'd like to confirm
Miss Morstan's name
is on the group's
register as a formality.
I assume you have it on you.
[MILVERTON grunts]
[MARY gasps]
Mary!
[HUDSON gasps]
[MILVERTON chuckles]
[cackling]
[MILVERTON] I so do
love the follies of youth
and all the material
it ends up supplying me.
Satisfied?
Please, keep it.
That one is merely a copy.
The actual register
is quite secure.
Now then, returning
to the treasure.
I haven't the
slightest intention
of ceding an inch of ground.
I will be staying at the
Langham until noon on Saturday.
Do make the delivery
before I check out.
I'm sure you'll
come up with some
inventive way of
dredging the Thames.
Good day, gentlemen.
Damn him! That Milverton
is the devil himself!
He mentioned that
the actual list
was securely in his possession.
[HOLMES]
Every time he stays in London,
it's his practice to
rent out an entire floor
at the Langham Hotel.
But all blackmailers
tend to keep
evidentiary material in the
safest place available to them.
In Milverton's case,
that would be his
oceanfront villa in Brighton.
[HOLMES]
An eye for an eye.
I'll sneak into his mansion
while he's still away.
I insist on handling this,
so please, don't interfere.
[HUDSON gasps]
Let you handle everything?
Don't be ridiculous, Sherlock!
I'm coming with you!
We're going to see it
through, together!
This entire matter
concerned Mary and I
from the very beginning!
[HOLMES stammers]
After all, we are
partners, aren't we?!
We stick side by side!
Solving mysteries
or going to prison!
Heh. Sharing a room
with you in jail, too?
That should prove interesting.
Sadly, I doubt that'll happen.
[grunts]
For you see, my friend,
I, too, have a gift
when it comes to crime.
Can't approach from the east.
We would run the
risk of being spotted.
Just to be safe, we should
head from the west.
There's a flash of light,
first storey, west side.
What? No one should be home.
[gun firing]
Gunfire!
The devil? This
doesn't make sense.
Sherlock, what now?
[HOLMES]
So that's what this is about.
[HOLMES] I've misread
the whole situation.
[WATSON grunts]
How do you mean?
John, head back
towards the town,
once there, fetch the police.
And what are you going to do?
Stay here, observe.
After you've
summoned the police,
we'll retrieve the list
while they investigate.
I'll do as you say
as long as you stay put.
All right?
Of course. Hurry along, now.
[HOLMES]
Hmm.
[gun firing]
[HOLMES] They're having
a right proper shootout.
Getting in through the ground
floor will be difficult.
[HOLMES grunts]
[grunts]
[MILVERTON] I'm asking,
kindly lower your gun.
[MILVERTON] Let's be
civilized and discuss this.
Won't you hear me out?
That's the least you can do.
[HOLMES gasps]
[floor creaks]
[MILVERTON]
So, you've arrived,
and right at the moment
I was expecting you.
You've come just in time.
A second later,
I would have had
a hole between my eyes.
Welcome, Sherlock Holmes.
Since neither of you clearly
understand the situation,
allow me to explain it in full.
[HOLMES]
That won't be necessary.
Really, such a tortuously
roundabout way.
How vexing.
Blackmailing John's fiancée
was simply a means to an end.
You wanted to drag me
into this affair.
The treasure--
it was an errand made to
drive us into a corner
with no solution
other than wresting the
evidence from your possession.
Thus, why I'm here.
[MILVERTON chuckles]
If I may make a confession,
upon reading the report
that the Treasure
was thrown into the river
just as I planned,
I couldn't help but
laugh hysterically.
Well, let's hear it.
You used some similar
convoluted method
to ensure he
showed up, no doubt.
[MILVERTON] Astute, as always.
However, you can probably wager
a fair guess why I
required your presence.
You have a part
to play, detective.
To arrest the man who
stands before you--
Oh, how rude.
May I present
the guest of honor.
The British Empire's
greatest criminal mind...
[thunder roars]
[MILVERTON]
...the Lord of Crime.
[MILVERTON] The Lord
of Crime, in the flesh,
one Professor
William James Moriarty!
Such a shame there are no
spectators to this comedy.
The representatives of London's
duality: light and darkness.
You couldn't ask
for a better show.
[HARRY grunts]
An immovable object meets an
unstoppable force. Eh, Louis?
Right about now, I would
imagine your boss and mine
ought to be in the thick of it,
along with one other visitor.
A standoff, between my employer,
the professor,
and Sherlock Holmes.
[LOUIS]
Holmes is here?
[HARRY]
A bizarre drama is taking place,
one I wished to see.
Then again, we're
just the mercenaries.
We're being paid
to slow you down.
To buy enough time until
the performance concludes
and the curtains draw.
Heh.
[LOUIS grunts]
Brother.
[MILVERTON] Now then,
given the circumstances,
events can only
play out one way.
As follows, the detective
arrests the Lord of Crime.
[MILVERTON] Moriarty,
if you choose to shoot me,
I have made arrangements
for various media outlets
to reveal your
identity to the public.
However, if you are
willing to go along quietly,
I guarantee you will live
the remainder of your life
far from the spotlight.
After handing you over to
the government, of course.
You will be placed
under house arrest.
Furthermore, all your
wants and needs,
I guarantee they will
be taken care of.
As for you, Holmes,
unless you want your dear
friend's precious wedding
to be cancelled, you will
submit and do as I say.
But if you still have any
reason to doubt my word--
[HOLMES] No, I know you
believe everything you said.
If your only
objective was to create
this drama and it all
plays out to a tee,
I assume you will no longer
have any reason to continue
blackmailing Miss Marston.
That's right. Some commoner
girl with no news value?
She meant nothing to me
from the start.
This one, however...
You're standing face-to-face
with a mass murderer,
as if you would
allow him to slip away.
Holmes! Arrest the
Lord of Crime. Do it!
[MILVERTON chuckles]
[MILVERTON] I'm in a position of
superiority over both of you,
in every regard.
You're pawns in a game you
never had a chance of winning.
[MILVERTON cackling]
Are you finished?
[MILVERTON grunts, growls]
[HOLMES]
My word, you ramble on.
If you do consider
this a comedy,
I'm sorry, but you aren't
the king; you're a jester.
My dear fellow,
you've misread the
situation entirely.
And how's that?
Come on, since he's here,
that's undoubtedly the case.
Don't you agree with me, Liam?
[HOLMES chuckles, laughing]
Great to see you again!
I'm glad it was you.
To be honest, I couldn't bear
the thought if it wasn't.
Finally, a worthy opponent.
No one else would do.
Seeing you here...
Well, to say it was a
relief is an understatement.
[MILVERTON]
Wait.
This-- This doesn't make sense!
Why the casual banter?
Don't tell me...
Holmes and Moriarty...
It can't be!
If the two of them had been in
contact, I would have known!
A detective and
an arch criminal?
"Liam"? What the devil
are you talking about?
I demand you answer me,
Sherlock Holmes!
Liam, the only thing I want is
to rescue my partner's marriage.
I'm fine with
whatever becomes of me.
So what about you?
Do you care if he reveals
your name to the world?
[MILVERTON gasps]
Hardly, since that was
always my intention.
Then we've reached our decision.
Wait a minute!
You can't kill me!
I-- The evidence!
I'll make it public!
[HOLMES]
No, you won't.
You may have the evidence,
but you haven't arranged
for it to be published.
You said yourself that
Mary had no news value,
don't you remember?
[grunts]
I thought as much. Whenever
someone sees right through you,
you're prone to
clenching your back teeth.
Yes, like that.
Hold on!
[MILVERTON]
This is impossible.
Choosing to be so irrational.
One I could understand,
but both of them?
[MILVERTON grunts]
[MILVERTON gasps, grunts]
[HOLMES] Your exit's not
your choice--it's mine.
- -[clang]
- -[HARRY grunts]
[BOTH gasp]
[HOLMES]
After all this,
I still can't definitively prove
you're the Lord of Crime.
[HOLMES] Meanwhile,
you've made me a hero
who exposed the misdeeds
of the nobility.
I was always
a step behind you.
Trapped, dancing in
the palm of your hand.
[HOLMES]
Still, though...
It's not as though that means
I'm completely
devoid of free will.
You never expected me
to kill Milverton.
[HOLMES] Don't assume everyone
will conform to your whims.
Least of all, me.
The game's afoot, and
there's no going back, Liam!
I swear I will unravel
your tangled web
and apprehend you my own way.
[WILLIAM chuckles]
[WILLIAM] And my
response to that challenge
is the same as before.
"Come and catch me if you can,
Sherlock Holmes."
Yes. I'll see you soon.
My patron got himself killed.
Was only a matter
of time, I suppose.
No reason to be
on the clock anymore.
[HARRY whistles]
[RUSKIN grunts]
[GOSLING grunts]
The show's over.
Hopefully, I'll never have to
cross paths with you again.
[door slams]
[LOUIS]
If Milverton is dead,
then where are
Holmes and William?
It was a true privilege, sir.
[WATSON gasps]
The villa!
Uh!
[WATSON]
Sherlock!
Are you...?
Yes. I'm fine. Thanks, though.
he evidence against
Mary is gone; she's free.
[gasps]
[POLICEMAN 22A] Mister Holmes!
What is the meaning of all this?
Please explain yourself at once.
Very well.
There'll be a lot of paperwork,
but here is the short version.
[HOLMES] This is the gun
I used to kill Milverton.
You may arrest me now.
[POLICE gasp]
What?! You killed him?
John, the wedding--
I'm sorry, I don't think
I'll be able to attend.
[WATSON gasps]
[POLICEMAN 22A]
We have no choice. Take him in!
[POLICE]
Sir!
[whimpers]
[WATSON]
You promised me.
I thought we were
partners until the end!
[WATSON]
Sherlock!
Although we're rid
of that pest, Milverton,
Holmes was unfortunately the one
that ended up
pulling the trigger.
You aren't to blame
for this, Brother.
There's no question he
had his own motivations
for shooting that man.
[WILLIAM]
I have a confession, Louis.
I never meant to let him become
a murderer as soon as this.
[gasps]
[WILLIAM]
I thought that for him,
killing another would be
the most difficult
hurdle to overcome.
[WILLIAM]
But once you kill one person,
murdering another
makes no difference.
Meaning,
that in all likelihood,
he'll hunt me down,
and when he does...
...he'll aim to end my life.
[HOLMES] Next time on
Moriarty the Patriot  :
"The Final Problem, Act One."